This is actually a painting
في الواقع هذه لوحة
that hangs at the Countway Library at Harvard Medical School.
معلقة في مكتبة كاونت واي بمدرسة الطب جامعة هارفرد
And it shows the first time an organ was ever transplanted.
وهي تبين أول مرة تتم فيها زراعة عضو.
In the front, you see, actually, Joe Murray
في المقدمة ترون "جو موراي"
getting the patient ready for the transplant,
يُعد المريض لعملية الزراعة
while in the back room you see Hartwell Harrison,
بينما في الغرفة الخلفية ترون "هارتويل هاريسون",
the Chief of Urology at Harvard,
عميد قسم الامراض البولية و التناسلية بهارفرد,
actually harvesting the kidney.
وهو بالفعل "يحصد" الكلية.
The kidney was indeed the first organ
الكلية هي بالفعل أول عضو
ever to be transplanted to the human.
يتم زراعته في الانسان.
That was back in 1954,
كان هذا عام 1954.
55 years ago.
منذ 55 عاماً
Yet we're still dealing with a lot of the same challenges
كانوا يتعاملون مع الكثير من التحديات نفسها
as many decades ago.
الموجودة منذ عقود كثيرة مضت.
Certainly many advances, many lives saved.
بالتأكيد تقدموا كثيراً , و أنقذت حياة الكثيرين
But we have a major shortage of organs.
ولكننا نعاني من نقص شديد في الأعضاء.
In the last decade the number of patients
في العقد الماضي, عدد المرضى
waiting for a transplant has doubled.
المنتظرين لعملية الزرع قد تضاعف.
While, at the same time, the actual number of transplants
بينما, في الوقت نفسه, عدد عمليات الزرع التى تمت بالفعل
has remained almost entirely flat.
قد استمر تقريبا كما هو.
That really has to do with our aging population.
وهذا بالطبع له علاقة باستمرار اعمار السكان في الزيادة.
We're just getting older.
نحن فقط نزداد في السن.
Medicine is doing a better job
علم الطب يتحسن اداءه باستمرار
of keeping us alive.
لإبقائنا احياء.
But as we age, our organs tend to fail more.
و لكن كلما كبرنا في السن, تميل اعضائنا الى الفشل و التعطل اكثر.
So, that's a challenge,
إذن فهذا تحدي,
not just for organs but also for tissues.
ليس فقط للأعضاء و لكن للأنسجة ايضاً.
Trying to replace pancreas,
في محاولة لإستبدال بنكرياس.
trying to replace nerves that can help us with Parkinson's.
أو في محاولة لإستعاضة أعصاب لتساعدنا مع مرض شلل الرعاش "الباركينسون"
These are major issues.
هذه مشاكل مهمة و اساسية.
This is actually a very stunning statistic.
هذه في الواقع إحصائية مذهلة.
Every 30 seconds
كل 30 ثانية,
a patient dies from diseases
يموت مريض بسبب مرض ما كان
that could be treated with tissue regeneration or replacement.
يمكن معالجته بواسطة تجديد أو أستعاضة الأنسجة.
So, what can we do about it?
إذن, ماذا يمكننا ان نفعل في هذا الشان؟
We've talked about stem cells tonight.
لقد تحدثنا عن الخلايا الجذعية الليلة.
That's a way to do it.
وهي احد الحلول المتاحه.
But still ways to go to get stem cells into patients,
و لكن مازال هناك الكثير لجعل الخلايا الجذعية في المرضى,
in terms of actual therapies for organs.
كعلاج فعلي للأعضاء.
Wouldn't it be great if our bodies could regenerate?
ألن يكون رائعاً لو كانت لأجسامنا القدرة على التجدد؟
Wouldn't it be great if we could actually harness the power
ألن يكون رائعاً لو إستطعنا ان نسخر قدرات
of our bodies, to actually heal ourselves?
اجسامنا, فنستطيع شفاء انفسنا بالفعل؟
It's not really that foreign of a concept, actually;
إنه ليس بالمفهوم الغريب, في الواقع
it happens on the Earth every day.
إنه يحدث على الأرض كل يوم.
This is actually a picture of a salamander.
هذه صورة لحيوان سمندر.
Salamanders have this amazing capacity to regenerate.
لفئة السمندر قدرعة عجيبة على التجدد.
You see here a little video.
هنا ترون فيديو قصير.
This is actually a limb injury in this salamander.
في الواقع هذه اصابة لأحد اطراف هذا السمندر.
And this is actually real photography,
و هذه صور حقيقية
timed photography, showing how that limb regenerates
صور متعاقبة ترينا كيف يتجدد هذا الطرف
in a period of days.
في بضعة ايام.
You see the scar form.
ترون تكون الندبة.
And that scar actually grows out
و هذه الندبة بالفعل تكبر
a new limb.
و تتحول الى طرف جديد.
So, salamanders can do it.
إذن السمندر يستطيع التجدد.
Why can't we? Why can't humans regenerate?
لماذا لا نستطيع نحن؟ لماذا لا يستطيع الانسان ان يتجدد؟
Actually, we can regenerate.
في الواقع, نحن نستطيع التجدد
Your body has many organs
في جسدك العديد من الأعضاء
and every single organ in your body
و كل عضو منها
has a cell population
فيه تجمع للخلايا
that's ready to take over at the time of injury. It happens every day.
على إستعداد ان يتولى الأمور في وقت الأصابة. هذا يحدث كل يوم.
As you age, as you get older.
كلما ازددت في العمر و كبرت.
Your bones regenerate every 10 years.
تتجدد عظامك كل 10 اعوام.
Your skin regenerates every two weeks.
تتجدد بشرتك كل اسبوعين.
So, your body is constantly regenerating.
اذن فجسدك يتجدد بإستمرار.
The challenge occurs when there is an injury.
التحدي يكمن عندما تحدث إصابة.
At the time of injury or disease,
في وقت الإصابة أو المرض
the body's first reaction
رد فعل الجسم الأول
is to seal itself off from the rest of the body.
هو أن يعزل الإصابة عن باقي الجسم.
It basically wants to fight off infection,
فهي في الأساس تريد ان تحارب العدوى و التلوث
and seal itself, whether it's organs inside your body,
و يعزل نفسه سواء كان عضوا داخل الجسم
or your skin, the first reaction
أو البشرة, أول رد فعل
is for scar tissue to move in,
هو ان يتحرك نسيج الندبة للداخل
to seal itself off from the outside.
ليعزل نفسه عن الخارج.
So, how can we harness that power?
إذن فكيف نتمكن من تسخير تلك القدرة؟
One of the ways that we do that
إحدى الطرق لفعل ذلك,
is actually by using smart biomaterials.
يتم في الواقع بإستخدام مواد عضوية ذكية.
How does this work? Well, on the left side here
كيف يتم هذا؟ حسنا, على اليسار هنا
you see a urethra which was injured.
ترون إصابة في مجرى البول.
This is the channel that connects the bladder to the outside of the body.
هذه هي القناة التي تصل من المثانة إلى الخارج.
And you see that it is injured.
و ترون انها مصابة.
We basically found out that you can use these smart biomaterials
وقد إكتشفنا انه من الممكن إستخدام هذه المواد العضوية الذكية
that you can actually use as a bridge.
بالفعل يمكن أن تكون بمثابة جسر
If you build that bridge, and you close off
إذا بنيت هذا الجسر و ابقيته بعيدا
from the outside environment,
عن البيئة الخارجية,
then you can create that bridge, and cells
اذا اوجدت هذا الجسر تستطيع الخلايا
that regenerate in your body,
التي تقوم بالتجدد داخل الجسم
can then cross that bridge, and take that path.
أن تعبر هذا الجسر و تكمل الطريق.
That's exactly what you see here.
و هذا بالظبط ما ترونه هنا.
It's actually a smart biomaterial
هذه في الواقع مادة حيوية ذكية
that we used, to actually treat this patient.
استخدمت بالفعل لعلاج هذا المريض.
This was an injured urethra on the left side.
هذا كان مجرى البول المصاب على اليسار.
We used that biomaterial in the middle.
استخدمنا المادة العضوية التي في المنتصف.
And then, six months later on the right-hand side
ثم, بعد ستة اشهر , على اليمين
you see this reengineered urethra.
ترون القناة البولية المعاد هندستها.
Turns out your body can regenerate,
اذن يتضح ان جسدك بالفعل يستطيع التجدد
but only for small distances.
ولكن لمسافات قصيرة فقط
The maximum efficient distance for regeneration
اقصى مسافة فعاله للتجدد
is only about one centimeter.
هي حوالي سينيميتر واحد فقط.
So, we can use these smart biomaterials
إذن فيمكننا إستخدام المواد العضوية هذه
but only for about one centimeter
و لكن بمقدار سم واحد فقط
to bridge those gaps.
لردم تلك الفجوات.
So, we do regenerate, but for limited distances.
إذن فنحن بالفعل نتجدد و لكن لمسافات محدودة.
What do we do now,
فماذا نفعل الان
if you have injury for larger organs?
اذا اصيب احد الأعضاء الكبيرة؟
What do we do when we have injuries
ماذا نفعل لو لدينا إصابات
for structures which are much larger
في تكوينات اكبر بكثير
than one centimeter?
من سينيميتر واحد؟
Then we can start to use cells.
نبدأ في استخدام خلايا.
The strategy here, is if a patient comes in to us
الخطة هنا هي اذا جائنا مريض
with a diseased or injured organ,
بعضو مريض او مصاب
you can take a very small piece of tissue from that organ,
أن تاخذ قطعة صغيرة جدا من نسيج هذا العضو,
less than half the size of a postage stamp,
أقل من نصف حجم طابع بريد,
you can then tease that tissue apart,
و عندها نفصل هذا النسيج الى اجزاء
and look at its basic components,
و ننظر في مكوناته الأساسية
the patient's own cells,
الى خلايا المريض نفسه
you take those cells out,
و تفصل هذه الخلايا
grow and expand those cells outside the body in large quantities,
وتزرعها و تزيدها خارج الجسم بكميات كبيرة,
and then we then use scaffold materials.
ثم نستخدم خامات ناقلة
To the naked eye they look like a piece of your blouse,
وهي خامات تبدو للعين المجردة كإنها قطعة قماش من بلوزتك
or your shirt, but actually
أو قميصك , ولكنها في الحقيقة
these materials are fairly complex
هي خامات معقدة بشكل كبير
and they are designed to degrade once inside the body.
وهي مصممة بحيث تتحلل بعد وضعها داخل الجسم.
It disintegrates a few months later.
و تختفي بعدها ببضعة اشهر.
It's acting only as a cell delivery vehicle.
فهي تعمل فقط كمركبة لتوصيل الخلايا.
It's bringing the cells into the body. It's allowing
تحضر الخلايا الى داخل الجسم, سامحة
the cells to regenerate new tissue,
للخلايا ان تنتج نسيج جديد
and once the tissue is regenerated the scaffold goes away.
و بمجرد تكوين النسيج الجديد تختفي الناقلة.
And that's what we did for this piece of muscle.
و هذا ما فعلناه مع هذه القطعة العضلية
This is actually showing a piece of muscle and how we go through
هذا في الواقع قطعة من العضل و كيف ننظر خلال
the structures to actually engineer the muscle.
مكوناتها لنتمكن بالفعل من هندسة العضلة.
We take the cells, we expand them,
نأخذ الخلايا, نضاعفها
we place the cells on the scaffold,
نضع الخلايا على الناقلة,
and we then place the scaffold back into the patient.
ثم نعيد وضع الناقلة في جسم المريض.
But actually, before placing the scaffold into the patient,
و لكن في الحقيقة قبل وضع الناقلة في جسم المريض,
we actually exercise it.
نقوم بتمرينها.
We want to make sure that we condition
فنحن نريد التأكد من أن نعود
this muscle, so that it knows what to do
هذه العضلة بحيث تستطيع اداء مهمتها
once we put it into the patient.
بمجرد وضعها في جسم المريض.
That's what you're seeing here. You're seeing
و هذا ما ترونه هنا. انتم ترون
this muscle bio-reactor
مفاعل حيوي للعضلات
actually exercising the muscle back and forth.
يقوم بتمرين تلك العضلة ذهابا وإيابا.
Okay. These are flat structures that we see here,
حسنا ما نراه هنا هو تكوينات مسطحة
the muscle.
العضلة.
What about other structures?
ماذا عن التكوينات الاخرى؟
This is actually an engineered blood vessel.
هذا في الواقع وعاء دموي تمت هندسته.
Very similar to what we just did, but a little bit more complex.
مشابه جدا لما رأيناه الان و لكن بشئ من التعقيد.
Here we take a scaffold,
هنا نأخذ الناقلة,
and we basically -- scaffold can be like a piece of paper here.
ثم نقوم...الناقلة كأنها قطعة من الورق هنا.
And we can then tubularize this scaffold.
ثم نشكل الناقلة بشكل انبوبي.
And what we do is we, to make a blood vessel, same strategy.
و ما نفعله , لصنع وعاء دموي, هو نفس الطريقة.
A blood vessel is made up of two different cell types.
الوعاء الدموي مكون من نوعين مختلفين من الخلايا.
We take muscle cells, we paste,
نأخذ الخلايا العضلية, و ندهن
or coat the outside with these muscle cells,
أو نغطي الجزء الخارجي بهذه الخلايا,
very much like baking a layer cake, if you will.
تماما كما نفعل مع طبقات الكيك
You place the muscle cells on the outside.
نضع طبقة الخلايا العضلية في الخارج
You place the vascular blood vessel lining cells on the inside.
و نضع طبقة الخلايا المبطنة للوعاء الدموي في الداخل.
You now have your fully seeded scaffold.
الان لديك ناقلة مزروعة و مجهزة بالكامل.
You're going to place this in an oven-like device.
ثم نضعها في جهاز مثل الفرن.
It has the same conditions as a human body,
مجهز بنفس الظروف الموجودة بجسم الانسان,
37 degrees centigrade,
درجة حرارة 37
95 percent oxygen.
و 95% أكسجين
You then exercise it, as what you saw on that tape.
ثم نقوم بتمرينها كما رأينا من قبل
And on the right you actually see a carotid artery that was engineered.
و على اليمين هنا ترون شريان سباتي تمت هندسته بالفعل.
This is actually the artery that goes from your neck to your brain.
وهو الشريان الواصل من الرقبة الى المخ.
And this is an X-ray showing you
وهذه اشعة لتريكم
the patent, functional blood vessel.
الوعاء الدموي وهو عامل و مفعل
More complex structures
التركيبات الاكثر تعقيدا
such as blood vessels, urethras, which I showed you,
مثل الاوعية الدموية, مجرى البول كما رأيتم
they're definitely more complex
وهي بالتأكيد معقدة
because you're introducing two different cell types.
لأنك تقوم بإدخال نوعين مختلفين من الخلايا.
But they are really acting mostly as conduits.
ولكنها تعمل في الأغلب كقنوات
You're allowing fluid or air to go through
لتسمح بإنتقال السوائل أو الهواء
at steady states.
في الحالات المستقرة.
They are not nearly as complex as hollow organs.
وهي لا تقترب حتى من تعقيد الاعضاء المجوفة.
Hollow organs have a much higher degree of complexity,
الأعضاء المجوفة على درجة عالية جدا من التعقيد,
because you're asking these organs to act on demand.
لانك تطالب تلك الاعضاء أن تعمل عند الحاجة.
So, the bladder is one such organ.
فمثلا المثانه احد تلك الاعضاء
Same strategy, we take a very small piece of the bladder,
و بنفس الاستراتيجية السابقة نأخذ قطعة صغيرة جدا من المثانه
less than half the size of a postage stamp.
اصغر من نصف حجم طابع بريد
We then tease the tissue apart
ونفصل هذا النسيج عن بعضه
into its two individual cell components,
الى مكونيه الخلويين الأساسيين,
muscle, and these bladder specialized cells.
خلايا عضلية, و خلايا المثانة المتخصصة.
We grow the cells outside the body in large quantities.
و نزرع الخلايا خارج الجسم بكميات كبيرة.
It takes about four weeks to grow these cells from the organ.
تاخذ حوالي 4 أسابيع لزرع تلك الخلايا من العضو.
We then take a scaffold that we shape like a bladder.
ثم نأخذ الناقلة التي نشكلها على شكل مثانة.
We coat the inside with these bladder lining cells.
و نبطن السطح الداخلي بخلايا المثانة المبطنة
We coat the outside with these muscle cells.
و السطح الخارجي بالخلايا العضلية.
We place it back into this oven-like device.
و نضعها في الجهاز الشبيه بالفرن.
From the time you take that piece of tissue, six to eight weeks later
و بعد اخذ قطعة النسيج هذه من الجسم بحوالي 6 الى 8 أسابيع
you can put the organ right back into the patient.
تستطيع زرع العضو مرة اخرى داخل المريض.
This actually shows the scaffold.
هنا يوضح شكل الناقلة
The material is actually being coated with the cells.
المادة يتم تغطيتها بالفعل بالخلايا.
When we did the first clinical trial for these patients
عندما بدأنا أول تجربة فعلية لهؤلاء المرضى
we actually created the scaffold specifically for each patient.
صنعنا مادة ناقلة خاصة لكل مريض
We brought patients in,
أدخلنا المرضى,
six to eight weeks prior to their scheduled surgery, did X-rays,
وقبل موعد العملية ب 6 الى 8 اسابيع ,أخذنا اشعة
and we then composed a scaffold specifically for that patient's size
ثم صنعنا المادة الناقلة ملائمة بالضبط لحجم المريض
pelvic cavity.
لحجم الحوض
For the second phase of the trials
وفي المرحلة الثانية لتلك التجارب
we just had different sizes, small, medium, large and extra-large.
كان لدينا فقط احجام معينة مختلفة, صغير, متوسط, كبير, كبير جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true.
إنها الحقيقة
And I'm sure everyone here wanted an extra-large. Right?
انا متأكد أن الجميع هنا يريد الحجم الكبير جدا, أليس كذلك؟؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, bladders are definitely a little bit more complex
إذن فالمثانة بالتأكيد اكثر تعقيدا
than the other structures.
من التركيبات الأخرى.
But there are other hollow organs that have added complexity to it.
ولكن هناك اعضاء مجوفة أخرى بمزيد من التعقيد.
This is actually a heart valve, which we engineered.
هذا في الحقيقة صمام قلبي تمت هندسته
And the way you engineer this heart valve is the same strategy.
و تستخدم نفس الطريقة السابقة في هندسة هذا الصمام.
We take the scaffold, we seed it with cells,
نأخذ المادة الناقلة و نزرعها بالخلايا
and you can now see here, the valve leaflets opening and closing.
و كما ترون هنا , شرفات الصمام تفتح و تغلق
We exercise these prior to implantation.
و نقوم بتمرينها قبل زرعها.
Same strategy.
نفس الطريقة.
And then the most complex are the solid organs.
و اكثر الأعضاء تعقيدا هي الاعضاء المصمتة.
For solid organs, they're more complex
بالنسبة للاعضاء المصمتة, الموضوع أكثر صعوبة
because you're using a lot more cells per centimeter.
لأنك تستخدم عدد خلايا اكبر لكل سينتيمتر
This is actually a simple solid organ like the ear.
هذا مثلا عضو مصمت بسيط وهو الأذن
It's now being seeded with cartilage.
و هي الان تزرع بالمادة الغضروفية
That's the oven-like device;
وهذا الجهاز الشبيه بالفرن
once it's coated it gets placed there.
بمجرد تغطيتها توضع بالداخل
And then a few weeks later we can take out the cartilage scaffold.
ثم بضعة أسابيع بعد ذلك نخرج ناقلة الغضروف
This is actually digits that we're engineering.
و هذه في الواقع أصابع نقوم بهندستها.
These are being layered, one layer at a time,
يتم وضعها في طبقات, طبقة واحدة كل مرة
first the bone, we fill in the gaps with cartilage.
اولا العظم, ثم نملأ الفجوات بالمادة الغضروفية
We then start adding the muscle on top.
ثم نبدأ بإضافة العضلات فوقها
And you start layering these solid structures.
ثم نبدأ في وضع طبقات هذه التكوينات المصمته
Again, fairly more complex organs,
وهو مرة أخرى عضو أكثر تعقيدا
but by far, the most complex solid organs
و لكن حتى الان أكثر الأعضاء تعقيدا
are actually the vascularized, highly vascularized,
هي الأعضاء المليئة بالاوعية الدموية
a lot of blood vessel supply,
مزودة بالكثير من الأوعية الدموية
organs such as the heart,
أعضاء مثل القلب
the liver, the kidneys.
الكبد, الكلى
This is actually an example -- several strategies
و هذا مثال من استراتيجيات عديدة
to engineer solid organs.
لهندسة الأعضاء المصمتة.
This is actually one of the strategies. We use a printer.
وهذه واحدة من الطرق. نستخدم طابعة
And instead of using ink, we use -- you just saw an inkjet cartridge --
و بدلا من إستخدام الحبر, نستخدم...لقد رأيتم الان حبارة..
we just use cells.
نستخدم خلايا بدلا من الحبر.
This is actually your typical desktop printer.
هذا في الحقيقة هي نفس الطابعة الالكترونية العادية
It's actually printing this two chamber heart,
وهي "تطبع" هذا القلب المكون من غرفتين,
one layer at a time.
طبقة واحدة في المرة.
You see the heart coming out there. It takes about 40 minutes to print,
ترون القلب يخرج هناك. تأخذ حوالي 40 دقيقة للطباعة
and about four to six hours later
و بعدها بحوالي 4 الى 6 ساعات
you see the muscle cells contract.
ترون الخلايا العضلية تنقبض.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This technology was developed by Tao Ju, who worked at our institute.
هذه التكنولوجيا طورها "تاو جو", و كان يعمل بمعهدنا
And this is actually still, of course, experimental,
وهذا بالطبع مازال تحت الإختبار
not for use in patients.
ولم يستخدم في مرضانا.
Another strategy that we have followed
طريقة أخرى إتبعناها
is actually to use decellularized organs.
هي إستخدام الاعضاء مفككة الخلايا.
We actually take donor organs,
فنحن نأخذ أعضاء المتبرع,
organs that are discarded,
أو الاعضاء الغير مرغوب فيها
and we then can use very mild detergents
ثم نستخدم محللات مخففة جدا
to take all the cell elements out of these organs.
لأخذ العناصر الخلوية من تلك الأعضاء
So, for example on the left panel,
فمثلا على اللوحة اليسرى,
top panel, you see a liver.
اللوحة العليا , ترون كبد
We actually take the donor liver,
نحن نأخذ كبد المتبرع,
we use very mild detergents,
و نستخدم محللات خفيفة,
and we, by using these mild detergents, we take all the cells
ثم, بإستخدام تلك المحللات, نأخذ كل الخلايا
out of the liver.
خارج الكبد
Two weeks later, we basically can lift this organ up,
و بعد أسبوعين نستطيع أن نرفع هذا العضو
it feels like a liver,
انه يبدو كالكبد,
we can hold it like a liver,
نستطيع ان نمسكه كالكبد
it looks like a liver, but it has no cells.
انه يشبه الكبد و لكن بدون خلايا
All we are left with
كل ما تبقى لدينا
is the skeleton, if you will, of the liver,
هو هيكل الكبد
all made up of collagen,
كله مكون من الكولاجين
a material that's in our bodies, that will not reject.
وهي خامة لن ترفضها أجسامنا.
We can use it from one patient to the next.
نستطيع ان نستخدمها من مريض للاخر.
We then take this vascular structure
ثم نأخذ هذا التكوين ذو الاوعية الدموية
and we can prove that we retain the blood vessel supply.
فنستطيع ان نثبت انه بامكاننا الإحتفاظ بالتغذية الوعائية
You can see, actually that's a fluoroscopy.
كما ترون, في الحقيقة هذا فلوروسكوبي
We're actually injecting contrast into the organ.
نحن نحقن المادة المتباينة في العضو
Now you can see it start. We're injecting the contrast into the organ
الان ترونها تبدأ. يتم حقن المادة المتباينة في العضو
into this decellularized liver.
في الكبد منزوع الخلايا
And you can see the vascular tree that remains intact.
وتستطيعون رؤية الشجرة الوعائية قد بقيت كما هي
We then take the cells, the vascular cells,
نأخذ الخلايا , الخلايا الوعائية
blood vessel cells, we perfuse the vascular tree
خلايا الوعاء الدموي, و نتخلل الشجرة الوعائية
with the patient's own cells.
بخلايا المريض نفسه.
We perfuse the outside of the liver
نتخلل الجزء الخارجي للكبد
with the patient's own liver cells.
بخلايا كبد المريض نفسه
And we can then create functional livers.
و عندها نستطيع ان نصنع كبد فعال.
And that's actually what you're seeing.
وهو ما ترونه بالفعل
This is still experimental. But we are able to actually reproduce the functionality
انه ما زال تحت الإختبار و لكننا قادرون على إستعادة فعالية
of the liver structure, experimentally.
نسيج الكبد, بالتجربة
For the kidney,
بالنسبة للكلى,
as I talked to you about the first painting that you saw,
كما أخبرتكم عن اللوحة الأولى التي رأيتموها
the first slide I showed you,
أول صورة تم عرضها هنا
90 percent of the patients on the transplant wait list
90% من المرضى على لائحة إنتظار الزراعة
are waiting for a kidney, 90 percent.
في إنتظار كلية, 90%
So, another strategy we're following
وهناك طريقة أخرى نتبعها
is actually to create wafers
هي ان نصنع رقاقات
that we stack together, like an accordion, if you will.
ونكدسها فوق بعضها, كالاوكورديون. اذا اردنا القول
So, we stack these wafers together, using the kidney cells.
فنكدس تلك الرقاقات مع بعضها , بإستخدام خلايا الكلية
And then you can see these miniature kidneys that we've engineered.
و يمكنكم أن ترون هذه الكلى المصغرة التي هندسناها
They are actually making urine.
انها تصنع البول بالفعل.
Again, small structures, our challenge is how to make them larger,
مرة أخرى ,تكوينات صغيرة, و التحدي امامنا هو كيف نجعلهم أكبر
and that is something we're working on
وهو ما نعمل عليه في الوقت الحالي
right now at the institute.
الان في المعهد
One of the things that I wanted to summarize for you then
أحد الاشياء التي أريد تلخيصها لكم,
is what is a strategy that we're going for in regenerative medicine.
ماهية الاستراتيجية التي نتجه اليها في علم تجدد الانسجة
If at all possible,
إذا كان في الإمكان
we really would like to use smart biomaterials
هي أن يمكننا إستخدام المواد العضوية الذكية
that we can just take off the shelf
أن يمكننا أن نرفع الغطاء
and regenerate your organs.
و نجدد اعضائك
We are limited with distances right now,
نحن الان محددين في أطوال المواد
but our goal is actually to increase those distances over time.
وهدفنا الحالي هو زيادة تلك الاطوال مع الوقت.
If we cannot use smart biomaterials,
ولو لم نستطع استخدام المواد العضوية الذكية
then we'd rather use your very own cells.
فنفضل إستخدام خلاياك الخاصة
Why? Because they will not reject.
لماذا؟ لأن الجسم لن يرفضها
We can take cells from you,
نأخذ منك الخلايا
create the structure, put it right back into you, they will not reject.
نصنع التركيب المراد, نضعها في الجسم مرة اخرى و لن يتم رفضها
And if possible, we'd rather use the cells from your very specific organ.
و إذا امكن نفضل إستخدام الخلايا المحددة الخاصة لعضو بذاته
If you present with a diseased wind pipe
اذا اتيت بقصبة هوائية مريضة
we'd like to take cells from your windpipe.
نأخذ الخلايا من قصبتك الهوائية
If you present with a diseased pancreas
اذا اتيت ببنكرياس مريض
we'd like to take cells from that organ.
ناخذ منه الخلايا
Why? Because we'd rather take those cells
لماذا؟ لأننا نفضل ان نأخذ تلك الخلايا
which already know that those are the cell types you want.
التي تعلم بالفعل انها نوع الخلايا الذي تحتاجه
A windpipe cell already knows it's a windpipe cell.
خلية القصبة الهوائية تعلم بالفعل انها خلية قصبة هوائية
We don't need to teach it to become another cell type.
نحن لا نحتاج ان ندربها لتصبح خلية من نوع اخر.
So, we prefer organ-specific cells.
اذن فنحن نفضل الخلايا الخاصة بكل عضو
And today we can obtain cells from most every organ in your body,
و اليوم أصبح بأمكاننا أن نحصل على خلايا من كل عضو في جسمك تقريبا
except for several which we still need stem cells for,
ما عدا البعض الذي ما زلنا نحتاج الخلايا الجذعية للحصول على خلاياها
like heart, liver, nerve and pancreas.
مثل القلب, الكبد, الأعصاب و البنكرياس
And for those we still need stem cells.
لهؤلاء مازلنا نحتاج للخلايا الجذعية
If we cannot use stem cells from your body
واذا لم نتمكن من الحصول على خلايا جذعية من جسمك
then we'd like to use donor stem cells.
نستخدم خلايا جذعية من المتبرع
And we prefer cells that will not reject
و نحن نفضل الخلايا التي لن يرفضها الجسم
and will not form tumors.
و لن تكوِن أورام.
And we're working a lot with the stem cells that we
و نحن نعمل كثيرا مع خلايا جذعية
published on two years ago,
كما نشرنا منذ عامين
stem cells from the amniotic fluid,
خلايا جذعية حصلنا عليها من السائل الامنيوسي.
and the placenta, which have those properties.
و المشيمة, والتي لديها تلك الخصائص.
So, at this point, I do want to tell you that
وهنا اريد أن اخبركم
some of the major challenges we have.
بعض التحديات الكبيرة التي تواجهنا.
You know, I just showed you this presentation, everything looks so good,
أتعلمون, بعد ما اريتكم هذا العرض, كل شئ يبدو جيدا
everything works. Actually no,
كله يبدو فعالا.و لكن لا.
these technologies really are not that easy.
تلك التكنولوجيا في الواقع ليست بهذه السهولة
Some of the work you saw today
بعض ما رأيتموه اليوم
was performed by over 700 researchers
قد نفذه اكثر من 700 باحث
at our institute across a 20-year time span.
في معهدنا على مدى 20 عاما.
So, these are very tough technologies.
اذن فهي تكنولوجيا معقدة للغاية.
Once you get the formula right you can replicate it.
بمجرد حصولك على الصيغة الصحيحة يمكنك نسخها
But it takes a lot to get there.
ولكن تحتاج الكثير لتصل لتلك المرحلة
So, I always like to show this cartoon.
احب دائما ان اعرض هذا الكارتون.
This is how to stop a runaway stage.
هو يمثل كيف يمكنك ايقاف عربة طائشة.
And there you see the stagecoach driver,
و هنا ترون سائق العربة.
and he goes, on the top panel,
وهو يبدأ, في الصورة العليا
He goes A, B, C, D, E, F.
يقفز بين f,e,d,c,b,a
He finally stops the runaway stage.
حتى يتمكن في النهاية من إيقاف العربة
And those are usually the basic scientists,
وهوأساسا ما يفعله العلماء عادةً
The bottom is usually the surgeons.
الصورة السفلى تمثل نهج الجراحين غالبا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm a surgeon so that's not that funny.
أنا جراح لذلك هو ليس مضحكا للدرجة بالنسبة لي.
But actually method A is the correct approach.
و لكن في الحقيقة الطريقة الاولى هي الطريقة الصحيحة.
And what I mean by that is that anytime we've launched one of these technologies
و ما اعنيه بذلك هو انه وقتما نطلق احدى هذه التكنولوجيات
to the clinic,
للعمل بها في العيادة
we've made absolutely sure that we do everything we can
نكون قد تأكدنا تماما من اننا بذلنا كل ما في وسعنا
in the laboratory before we ever
في المعمل قبل حتى أن نفكر
launch these technologies to patients.
في إطلاقها للمرضى.
And when we launch these technologies to patients
و عندما نطلق تلك التكنولوجيات لعلاج المرضى
we want to make sure that we ask ourselves a very tough question.
فنحن نريد أن نتأكد تماما وأن نسأل أنفسنا سؤالا صعبا جدا
Are you ready to place this in your own loved one, your own child,
هل نحن على إستعداد أن نزرع مثل هذا العضو لأحد احبائنا, أولادنا
your own family member, and then we proceed.
أحد افراد عائلتنا؟...ثم بعدها نستمر
Because our main goal, of course,
لأن هدفنا الاساسي بالطبع
is first, to do no harm.
هو اولا, ان لا نسبب الاذى.
I'm going to show you now, a very short clip,
سأريكم الان مقطع فيديو قصير جدا.
It's a five second clip of a patient
مدته 5 ثواني لمريضة
who received one of the engineered organs.
تم علاجها بواحد من تلك الاعضاء التى تمت هندستها
We started implanting some of these structures
بدأنا في زراعة بعض هذه التركيبات
over 14 years ago.
منذ اكثر من 14 عاما.
So, we have patients now walking around with organs,
إذن فلدينا الان مرضى يمشون بيننا بأعضاء
engineered organs, for over 10 years, as well.
تمت هندستها ،و لما يزيد على 10 أعوام.
I'm going to show a clip of one young lady.
سأريكم الان مقطع فيديو لسيدة صغيرة
She had a spina bifida defect, a spinal cord abnormality.
كانت تعاني من مرض الصلب المشقوق, عيب خلقى في الحبل الشوكي
She did not have a normal bladder. This is a segment from CNN.
و لا تعمل مثانتها بشكل طبيعي. هذا مقطع من قناة CNN الإخبارية.
We are just taking five seconds.
سنأخذ فقط 5 ثواني.
This is a segment that Sanjay Gupta actually took care of.
هذه فقرة في الواقع اهتم بها "سانجاي جبتا"
Video: Kaitlyn M: I'm happy. I was always afraid
"انا سعيدة جدا. كنت دائما خائفة من أن"
that I was going to have like, an accident or something.
"تحدث لي حادثة أو شئ ما.."
And now I can just go and
"والان أستطيع ان"
go out with my friends,
"أخرج مع اصدقائي"
go do whatever I want.
"أستطيع أن افعل ما أريد"
Anthony Atala: See, at the end of the day, the promise of regenerative medicine
ارأيتم, في نهاية اليوم, ما يعد به الطب التجددي
is a single promise.
هو وعد واحد فقط
And that is really very simple,
وهو حقا بسيط للغاية.
to make our patients better.
جعل مرضانا بحال أفضل.
Thank you for your attention.
شكرا لإنتباهكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)